Good morning, this is Dan Margolies and I'm filling in for Rabbi
Linzer. He is still getting over a cold, so we wish him
רפואה שלמה. Refuah Shleimah. Today's דף Daf is going to go from
כ... Kaf... קכב, Kuf Kaf Bet, עמוד א. Amud Aleph. We're going
to start on the seventh wide line where it says
אמר מר. Amar Mar. Right? And today is May 23rd, and it's
the 27th of אייר. Iyar. This is indeed the יום. yom. This
is the 42nd day of the עומר, Omer, which is six full
weeks. So it's very exciting that we're six sevenths of the way
through. Okay.
So
the גמרא Gemara says, אמר מר. Amar Mar. So this is in
the discussion that we've been having of all of the different נחלות
Nachalot and all of the different ancestral pieces of land and all
sorts of things like that. So אמר מר, Amar Mar, one of
the אמוראים Amoraim said, עתידה ארץ ישראל שתחלק לשלושה עשר שבטים. Atida
Eretz Yisrael she-techalek l'shlosha asar shevatim. In the future, the Land of
Israel will not be divided for 12 tribes, but for 13 שבטים.
shevatim. Now it's not exactly clear why it's tribes where in the
context of the פסוקים Psukim from יחזקאל Yechezkel that describe the way
the land will be divided in the future. So we're going to
see: אידך למאן? t'idach l'man? So what's the 13th one for? אמר
רב חסדא: Amar Rav Chisda: לנשיא. l'Nasi. It's for the נשיא. Nasi.
Now we know
in יחזקאל Yechezkel there's a character called the נשיא Nasi who seems,
the door closed, who seems somewhat similar to a kind of a
king of some sort, but he's not called a king, he's called
a נשיא. Nasi. It's interesting, perhaps יחזקאל Yechezkel had a נבואה Nevuah
of the future times where even the supreme executive of the state
would not necessarily be a king.
But the point of this נשיא, Nasi, so he has certain special
קרבנות Korbanot to bring, he has a special place to sit in
the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, he has a certain special gate that
he's supposed to go through in the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. So
lots of different things about the נשיא Nasi in the towards the
end of יחזקאל, Yechezkel, and we read a number of those things
actually on different הפטרות. Haftarot. We have a הפטרה Haftarah for פרשת
החודש, Parshat HaChodesh, I think, which describes a lot about this נשיא
Nasi and his special קרבנות Korbanot and things like that in preparation
for פסח. Pesach.
So רב חסדא Rav Chisda says: לנשיא. l'Nasi. So that is there
are the 12 normal שבטים, Shevatim, which already is a little bit
of a confusion because do we count the two tribes of יוסף
Yosef together as one and we count לוי? Levi? Or do we
count לוי Levi to get no נחלה Nachala and do we count
the two tribes אפרים Ephraim and מנשה Menashe separately? But either way
you're going to get 12 and then number 13 is for the
נשיא. Nasi. The נשיא's Nasi family gets their own special inheritance which
is separate from the other שבטים. Shevatim.
Do you get the equal portions of the entire, I mean are
these disproportionate portions? Like this 13th as big as, you know?
I'm not sure it has to be proportional, it would seem very
unfair for one family
to
get one thirteenth of the entire Land of Israel. Also we know
יחזקאל Yechezkel describes somewhat different layout of the שבטים Shevatim as well.
Yeah.
Does this suggest the משיח? Moshiach?
Yeah,
for sure, of course, the נשיא. Nasi. One of the big debates
in how to understand יחזקאל Yechezkel is whether the נבואות Nevuot about
בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash were for בית שני Bayit Sheni or בית
שלישי. Bayit Shlishi. The conclusion in the Tannaitic period more was that
it doesn't make any sense if it was for בית שני. Bayit
Sheni. They saw the real בית שני, Bayit Sheni, so it must
be for בית שלישי. Bayit Shlishi. So that means then the נשיא
Nasi that's being described is referring to מלך המשיח Melech HaMoshiach in
some way. Or but but already it's a great paradox of יחזקאל.
Yechezkel. יחזקאל Yechezkel was a נביא Navi during the period of the
first גלות. Galus. So he, what he saw and what he's describing
could very well have been the second בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. And
then when they actually came to build the second בית המקדש Beit
HaMikdash they said, you know we have this book יחזקאל Yechezkel but
like let's not follow that, let's build it more similar to the
בית ראשון. Bayit Rishon. So in a sense there is this kind
of tension between what the נביא Navi saw and what sort of
actually happened in the בית שני Bayit Sheni period such that the
appropriate interpretation must be that his נבואה Nevua is talking about בית
שלישי Bayit Shlishi in some way.
So that wouldn't make much sense, would it?
Like why would you be talking about a בית שלישי? Bayit Shlishi?
Right, why would יחזקאל Yechezkel be talking during the first גלות Galus
before there's even a בית שני Bayit Sheni that he would have
a נבואה Nevua about בית שלישי? Bayit Shlishi?
So that's actually not so comforting, but like you know
the נביא Navi
says you'll be exiled again.
Well the first time we were only exiled for 70 years and
this time it's already been, you know, already close to 2,000 years.
So any answer to that? I don't know a good answer to
that except that's, you know, that's the way God works sometimes. There
is a, there is a, again נבואה, Nevua, the whole problem of
נבואה Nevua is that we can only understand it after the fact.
If it's something, if it's describing some future event or it's describing
the way something is going to be and then it turns out
not that way, well then it just means either that נבואה Nevua
didn't apply to that event, it applies to some other event, or
there was something that we did that changed the course of history.
The רמב"ן Ramban describes that as well. Yeah.
Is it consensus that this בית שלישי Bayit Shlishi is ימי המשיח
Yemei HaMoshiach as opposed
to...
Well, more or less those are the same. Meaning in order to
have a, there's a whole, someone I think did this online once
and sort of proved that it's impossible, which is that there are
whole series of prerequisites for different parts of the ideal הלכתית halachic
society. You need כהנים Kohanim who are טהור, tahor, you need a
בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, you need a king, you need a סנהדרין.
Sanhedrin. So all these different pieces and how do they line up
in such a way you need this in order to get this,
and you need this in order to get this, ends up being
some kind of a loop.
So the solution has to be that משיח Mashiach will come and
because we need someone to tell us who are the כהנים מיוחסים,
Kohanim Meyuchasim, we need someone to tell us who's from the family
of דוד המלך. Dovid HaMelech. So we need a נביא Navi in
order to identify a lot of those pieces and where's the מזבח
Mizbeach supposed to go we need a נביא Navi for. So there
are a lot of different things
where we need a נביא Navi to tell us where it is.
Yeah, and that's the basic consensus view?
I would say that's the majority view. Obviously the question of, you
know, in what way would it be possible, you know, in a
pre-משיח Mashiach period to go and rebuild the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash,
or would rebuilding the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash itself be something that
qualifies someone to be a candidate to be considered as the משיח,
Mashiach, which is what the רמב"ם Rambam already writes about in הלכות
מלכים Hilchos Melachim towards the end.
Just trying to understand. So this נשיא Nasi we're saying is משיח
Mashiach and that would sort of be the precursor or usher in
מלכות בית דוד, Malchus Beis Dovid, the resurgence of מלכות בית דוד.
Malchus Beis Dovid. That's what you're saying, so it's going to go
to מלכות בית דוד. Malchus Beis Dovid.
Right. So but it's not part of the שבט יהודה, Shevet Yehuda,
it's a separate נחלה Nachala for the נשיא Nasi and his family.
Based on those פסוקים Pesukim in יחזקאל, Yechezkel,
but it's not necessarily including ירושלים Yerushalayim because ירושלים Yerushalayim belongs to
כל השבטים. kol hashavatim.
Right, so not ירושלים, Yerushalayim, somewhere else, some portion of land.
It might not even be where the capital is.
It's probably not necessarily in the capital. The king wants to have
some vacation, summer home somewhere. So all of those questions obviously we're
not really going to be able to resolve fully. And חז"ל Chazal
already had identified the fact that the words in נביא יחזקאל Navi
Yechezkel even contradicts himself in different places and it's a very complex
book to try to parse.
That's why they almost wanted to be גנוז.
gonez. They wanted to have be גנוז gonez the ספר יחזקאל Sefer
Yechezkel and there are a lot of different דרשות drashot already in
the תנאי Tannaitic period to try to save יחזקאל Yechezkel from being
considered either heretical or controversial, but that's a topic for another time.
Okay, so אמר רב חסדא לנשיא דכתיב
והעובד העיר יעבדוהו מכל שבטי ישראל. Amar Rav Chisda le-Nasi de-ksiv ve-ha-oved
ha-ir yaavduhu mikol shivtei Yisrael. So the point we're focusing on in
this פסוק pasuk is that the נשיא, Nasi, העובד, ha-oved, he's the
one who is working in service, העיר יעבדוהו, ha-ir yaavduhu, so the
city that is going to serve him is going to be מכל
שבטי ישראל. mikol shivtei Yisrael. So in some sense the property where
he has the power to be the ruling monarch is an area
which is considered to be מכל שבטי ישראל. mikol shivtei Yisrael. It's
been taken out of the properties from all other שבטים. shvatim. In
other words, that it's a reallocated separate piece of נחלה. nachala. In
fact though, there are other פסוקים pesukim that would perhaps be a
better proof that the נשיא nasi gets a special נחלה nachala towards
the end of יחזקאל Yechezkel as well, like I was saying from
the הפטרה haftarah of פרשת החודש Parshas HaChodesh and places like that.
Why the גמרא Gemara chooses this פסוק pasuk of all I was
somewhat surprised actually. So אמר ליה רב פפא לאביי. Amar leh Rav
Pappa le-Abaye. רב פפא Rav Pappa said to אביי, Abaye, אימא רונגר
בעלמא. eima rungar be-alma. So maybe it's just talking about what's רונגר?
rungar? One second.
So the רשב"ם Rashbam says שכירים בעלמא לעבוד בו כתלמידים לרב. schirim
be-alma la-avod bo ke-talmidim le-rav. Hired hand? Maybe he's just talking about
hired workers. So it's not talking about his נחלה, nachala, he's just
talking about some field that he has workers over. And it's very
interesting the way the רשב"ם Rashbam says hired workers like students who
serve their teacher, which is a fascinating, right, obviously the teacher is
usually hired, the students hire the teacher. We had that מחלוקת machlokes
back in בבא מציעא Bava Metzia about
who's considered in charge of whom. Is the teacher in charge of
the students or the students in charge of the teacher? How does
that hierarchy and power dynamic play out? It's very interesting, and for
different kinds of
cases
of ריבית. ribbis. There was that discussion there about, oh, is it
ריבית ribbis because you're working for me or vice versa. Okay, so
אמר ליה
רב פפא לאביי,
Amar leh Rav
Pappa le-Abaye, so אימא רונגר בעלמא. eima rungar be-alma. So maybe it's
just talking about workers in his field, in his properties, so it's
not actually talking about that he has...
You have workers from all the tribes?
Right, he'll have laborers who come from the different tribes. It doesn't
mean that his ancestral land is going to be a separate piece
of land from everyone else's.
So לא סלקא דעתך דכתיב... lo salka da'atach de-ksiv...
He said there's a note here referring to יחזקאל Yechezkel where at
the end it says at the end of the verse it says
the נשיא nasi will receive this portion in addition to the temple
area and ירושלים. Yerushalayim.
So the נשיא nasi but I thought ירושלים Yerushalayim is not anyone's,
it's certainly not the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, that's the whole point.
And that's part of what's confusing about this passage in יחזקאל Yechezkel
is that it seems to contradict other things that we know in
different places. So we usually say ירושלים לא נתחלקה לשבטים Yerushalayim lo
nitchalka lishvatim that ירושלים Yerushalayim is kept separate from the שבטים shvatim
and at the same time it sounds like ירושלים Yerushalayim is the
domain of this
נשיא... nasi...
Not the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash.
Well the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash in so it must be in
some way that it doesn't violate the need for the בית המקדש
Beit HaMikdash to be shared by all the שבטים. shvatim. Yeah.
How
do you work that out?
So is that what they mean by the thirteenth מחלוקת? machaloket?
Like twelve שבטים shvatim plus the נשיא. nasi.
12 plus the נשיא. nasi. That's our working theory right now.
Are we going to change it?
I don't think so. I think this is more or less is
the conclusion of this סוגיא sugya but it's just...
Yeah
12 tribes plus the thirteenth for the נשיא. nasi. Cause it says
also the חרם cherem that goes to the נשיא nasi I think
in יחזקאל Yechezkel it talks about.
Okay so that's a problem right?
Cause it's a problem in that it changes the order of things
from what we were used to.
Sure. But even without the נשיא nasi like
who are the 12 tribes? Exactly. I mentioned that before is it
that we count יוסף Yosef as two and לוי Levi doesn't count
at all?
And שמעון Shimon gets one
and שמעון Shimon whatever happened to שמעון. Shimon. So if you take
a look towards again this is in Messianic times in some way
שמעון Shimon will be back. The big question obviously is לוי Levi
do לוי Levi are לוי Levi still going to have to live
in separate cities or are they going to get a full נחלה
nachala like everyone else? So you look in the end of יחזקאל
Yechezkel there's a lot there.
Okay.
Okay והנותר לנשיא מזה ומזה לתרומת הקדש ולאחוזת העיר. v'hanosar l'nasi mizeh
umizeh litrumat hakodesh v'la'achuzat ha'ir.
Okay. So the other פסוק pasuk another פסוק pasuk in יחזקאל Yechezkel
says whatever was left over the remnant goes to the נשיא nasi
מזה ומזה mizeh umizeh from this one and from this one לתרומת
הקדש litrumat hakodesh as a dedication to the temple ולאחוזת העיר v'la'achuzat
ha'ir and for control of the city. So there it also sounds
like the נשיא nasi actually has property rights over the קדש kodesh
over the עיר ir which is ירושלים Yerushalayim and also control מזה
ומזה mizeh umizeh from all the different tribes. Okay ולא נתחלקה אלא
לכספים v'lo nitchalka ela leksafim
maybe you could say that when it was divided now is this
talking about the נשיא nasi or is this talking about the original
נחלה nachala with יהושע Yehoshua we're kind of flipping back and forth
a little bit. It seems to me that this is actually talking
about יהושע Yehoshua now. So it says ולא נתחלקה אלא לכספים. v'lo
nitchalka ela leksafim. Oh no is that coming up later? That comes
up later I'm sorry. Okay. So ולא נתחלקה אלא לכספים v'lo nitchalka
ela leksafim it was only divided
in terms of cash value. That is when they would subdivide the
לכספים leksafim part meaning that the difference in the size of the
land and the which part the נשיא nasi gets to control that's
more about a kind of a cash value and
less about
actual holdings. So the רשב"ם Rashbam says למאי הלכתא קאמר שיהיו
מעלין כספים זה לזה. lemai hilchata ka'amar sheyehu ma'alin kesafim zeh lazeh.
That that there's I think what he's saying is a kind of
a מעילה me'ilah between the money used between different, it's a tribute.
Right. It's like a kind of a tribute like a kind of
a tax that the נשיא's nasi control over the properties is not
that he has that as a נחלה nachala but he has it
just to be able to tax to have a property tax. So
he can tax the property rights? I'm not exactly sure. Okay.
Do you know I understand that everyone else's I don't understand in
terms of בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash like what does...
Yeah I don't know in terms of בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash I
don't understand. אלא לכספים שנאמר בין רב למעט
ela leksafim shene'emar
bein rav lime'at it's between whether for those with a larger property
or a smaller property. ולמאי אילימא לשופרא וסניא ulema ileima leshufra vesanya
to okay so maybe we're talking about so no this is talking
about the original נחלה. nachala. So in the time when they divided
the land in the time of יהושע Yehoshua did they have to
equilibrate the different plots of land between different people inheriting them. So
when the land was subdivided so first of all did they buy
people off onto if you had a better piece of land so
you had to pay a little bit of cash to equalize with
someone who maybe got a worse piece of land because it says
בין רב למעט bein rav lime'at whether you have more or less
it's still you're still going to get an equal share.
Okay למאי lemai so what is that coming to teach? אילימא לשופרא
וסניא ileima leshufra vesanya maybe for very nice land or very not
so nice land so לשופרא וסניא אטו בשופטני עסקינן. leshufra vesanya atu
beshoftani askinan. So maybe we're... Yeah so meaning so what are we
talking about? אלא לקורבה ורחוקה. ela lekurva verachuka. So are we talking
about...
בשופטני עסקינן? beshuftani askinan? Are we really talking about, you know, dumb
people? Like, it's so obvious that what you're talking when that when
you would, if it would be higher quality land or lower quality
land, of course you would need to balance it out by by
value. The question then, meaning they would assess the size of the
land in proportion to the quality of the arable arable land. So
the problem here is not not that the land will be of
different value because it's actually able to produce more or not. The
reason the land will be worth more, so the גמרא Gemara says,
אלא לקורבה ולרחוקה. ela lekurva velirchoka. It's about how close or far
away your field is from the city. So you want to be
able to be near the city because you have to, you know,
go to market and things like that. But if you're going to
be living on a farm, you also want your farm to be,
you know, good high-producing crop land. So the value of the land
will also be based on how close you are to an urban
center, and that's going to need some kind of compensation or adjustment
to compensate for the value.
Meaning so of course it's not just... meaning the question is what
are the determinants of value. Right. So obviously the quality of the
land. So another one is also the proximity to the city.
Right. Number one is the size of the land, which we would
assume is the first criterion. The second would be the quality, the
production value of the land. And the third is location, location, location,
as the real estate agents say.
So whatever it seems, what does that mean you're going to compensate?
Who are you going to pay,
like the rest of בני ישראל? Bnei Yisrael? Well so they probably
would buy into some communal fund which would then pay back out
to those who got a worse property.
Why am I paying? It's just you just divide it up this
way. In other words, this is you get five dollars worth of
land, you get five dollars worth of land. No one's paying anything.
And then you know your five dollars of land may be this
big, your five dollars of land may be that big.
Right, so that's a question of whether or not are we talking
about a cash compensation or we talking about in land compensation? So
that was the גמרא Gemara had this question. So it says ולא
נתחלקה אלא בכספים, velo nitchaleka ela bechasafim, that it was divided for
cash value. So, but that's a question on the previous position. Right.
So that's it's a question.
So I would say the most obvious would be to say that
it should all go to real estate, but particularly what's bothering the
גמרא Gemara as well is as we know, real estate is considered
much more intrinsically valuable than cash. Even though it's less liquid, it's
it produces. It's an investment. So if you're going to say, "Oh,
I'll take a worse piece of land and I'll take cash," you've
gotten the short end of the deal because it's much better to
have a very productive piece of land that's going to serve you
forever. Right, it'll be forever, literally forever. So
it'll serve your whole family for centuries, you want to have a
piece of land which is going to be very productive and a
good piece of farm land and you're probably not going to care
as much about cash right now. Even right, because the best thing
you could do with cash would be to reinvest it in in
buying a piece of real estate for forty-nine years
and then it's going to revert. So all of those pieces here
seem to I think it's still a קשיא kasha on the way
the גמרא Gemara is trying to resolve this. The best solution would
be to try to say like Michael is suggesting that it should
just be re-divided based on land as per its value that everyone
gets an equal value, but it's a good question. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says כתנאי. ketannai. This opinion of the אמוראים Amoraim is
like the opinions of
the
תנאים. Tannaim. רבי אליעזר אומר בכספים העלוה רבי יהושע אומר בקרקע העלוה.
Rabbi Eliezer omer bechasafim he'aluha Rabbi Yehoshua omer becharka he'aluha. So it's
a מחלוקת. machlokes. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer thinks like we just said
that it was based on cash value
and רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua says no, it would actually just be
that they would subdivide the land in such a way that the
land compensates for that value. Yeah.
Didn't you say it was revert at the end of forty-nine years?
If you bought if you bought land. Meaning I said if the
compensation you got was cash, the best investment you can do with
cash is to buy a piece of land, but then you've only
got it for forty-nine years. It's not going to be a permanent
permanent distribution. Right,
the whole point of this is that this is the נחלה. nachala.
So this is the permanent ancestral land. Right. Okay. So בקרקע העלוה
ולא נתחלקה אלא בגורל becharka he'aluha velo nitchaleka ela begoral and they
agree that it was subdivided by by a lottery. Okay, שנאמר אך
בגורל. shene'emar ach begoral. The פסוק pasuk says. Okay. So תנא אך
בגורל, tanna ach begoral, so why does it say אך בגורל? ach
begoral? אך ach is usually an exclusion. The word אך ach means
to exclude something. So who is being excluded? יצאו יהושע וכלב. yatzu
Yehoshua veChalev. יהושע Yehoshua and כלב Calev did not participate in the
גורל. goral. We know that
יהושע Yehoshua and כלב Calev were the only males who were able
to enter the land who were above the age of sixty. That
is, they were the only men who were over twenty when they
left מצרים. Mitzrayim.
So what did we just have before that they
may have and they may have been given we're going to see
they were given... an especial piece of land as part of their
inheritance as well, unique to them because of the role that they
played when they were part of the מרגלים Meraglim and their service
to בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael in such a way, and כלב Kalev
especially had a special relationship to the city of חברון, Hevron, we're
going to see.
Okay, so למי? L'mai? אילימא דלא שקול כלל, Ilema d'lo shakol klal,
so maybe you're saying they didn't count in the גורל Goral at
all.
I'm
trying to yesterday also he said
לא נגזרה גזירה אלא על יתר מבן שישים, Lo nigzera gezeira ela
al yeter miben shishim, so they're not the only ones over 60,
but they were the only ones between 20 and 60 at that
time maybe.
The only ones between 20 and 60? Okay, fine, right, so there
were people who were over the age of 100, okay, not probably
not so many. There was also
סרח בת אשר Serach Bat Asher and a few others of the
women from earlier generations and יוכבד בת לוי, Yocheved Bat Levi, so
you have some people but more I was oversimplifying.
Okay, so it says אך בגורל, Ach begoral, what does it mean
אך בגורל? Ach begoral? יצאו יהושע וכלב. Yatzu Yehoshua v'Kalev. למי? L'mai?
אילימא דלא שקיל כלל, Ilema d'lo shakil klal, maybe they weren't counted
in the גורל Goral at all? So השתא דלאו דידהו שקול, Hashta
d'lav didhu shakol, so דידהו מבעיא? didhu mibaya? So if you're going
to tell me that their properties weren't counted
because they're not part of
the מרגלים, Meraglim, right? If you look in דלאו דידהו, d'lav didhu,
so חלק מרגלים כדאמרן בפרקין דלעיל, Chelek Meraglim k'damarn b'pirkin d'leil, that
is because they were the good מרגלים, Meraglim, they got the properties
from the other the other מרגלים Meraglim like it's kind of an
interesting replacement process, right? בנות צלפחד Bnot Tzelafchad had to get from
their father and that was a whole big struggle, but here it
certainly makes a certain amount of sense that of the 12 מרגלים,
Meraglim, the two who were good would somehow would get that from
those who failed of the other ten מרגלים. Meraglim. Okay, so it
says דידהו שקול דידהו מבעיא? didhu shakul didhu mibaya? אלא שלא נטלו
בגורל. Ela shelo natlu b'goral. They didn't take it by a random
lottery. When they were assigned properties it didn't go
by the lottery. That is, they still got a permanent נחלה, nachala,
they got their land, but it wasn't assigned to them by chance
by the גורל, goral, it was assigned, it was pre-decided
which property, a certain amount, יהושע Yehoshua was already in charge at
the time. So if יהושע Yehoshua is in charge, that's part of
also why he gets to have the land without any
competition in the lottery process אלא על פי השם, ela al pi
Hashem, it was assigned by God directly. יהושע דכתיב על פי השם
נתנו לו את העיר אשר שאל את תמנת סרח בהר אפרים.
Yehoshua d'chtiv al pi Hashem natnu lo et ha'ir
asher sha'al et Timnat Serach b'har Ephraim.
So God designated to יהושע Yehoshua that he should get the city
of תמנת סרח Timnat Serach
in the mountainous region of אפרים. Ephraim. So we have אפרים, Ephraim,
right? אפרים Ephraim is here, it's north of בנימין, Binyamin, it's in
the שומרון. Shomron. So you have a lot of nice mountains there.
So יהושע Yehoshua had a city there. כתיב סרח וכתיב חרס, Ctiv
Serach u'ctiv Cheres, right? In one place it's called סרח Serach and
in one place it's called חרס. Cheres. חרס Cheres means pottery, right,
in ספר שופטים. Sefer Shoftim. So we have a problem why would
it be called חרס? Cheres? So אמר רבי אלעזר. amar Rabbi Elazar.
It is the same word just backwards. It is the same word
just backwards. So what does it come to teach us about the
city that the name switched from סרח Serach to חרס? Cheres? So
אמר רבי אלעזר בתחילה פירותיה כחרס. amar Rabbi Elazar batchila peroteha k'cheres.
Originally the fruits were totally dry and inedible like pottery
ולבסוף פירותיה מסריחין. u'l'basof peroteha masrichin.
And then in the end the fruits rotted.
Okay, so what? Stinking, right, מסריחין, masrichin, they spoil. Okay, ואיכא דאמרי
בתחילה מסריחין v'ika d'amri batchila masrichin and some say it was reversed.
Originally they were very rotten fruits ולבסוף כחרס u'l'basof k'cheres and at
the end they became like pottery. So I'm not sure which of
those is better. Meaning I'm not sure why the city that יהושע
Yehoshua inherited would have such terrible fruit, but that's kind of an
interesting מידה כנגד מידה mida k'neged mida which is that the bad
מרגלים Meraglim focused on the quality of the fruits of ארץ ישראל.
Eretz Yisrael. יהושע Yehoshua able to appreciate the quality of ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael despite questions about the fruit, right? Whether the fruits are
good, the fruits are bad, so maybe that's part of it. יהושע
Yehoshua inherited a land that he was able to appreciate even though
the fruit was terrible. I'm not sure. It's interesting.
There's a suggestion here that they're not talking about good or bad,
they're talking about whether they would be able to be stored for
a long time.
Ah, so if they're כחרס k'cheres it would be good because
they could be stored right away because
חרס cheres it stays for a long time. Ah, seems a bit
apologetic to me. Usually if you would describe oh this fruit is
like pottery I would say oh that's pretty terrible, right? Like you
take a bite of a peach and there's no sweetness and there's
no juice and it's just like dry crumbling. I'm not sure
what?
Right, the רשב"ם, Rashbam, yeah, no I'm just saying in terms of
you know it's trying to explain how it could be a good
thing, right. I'm thinking also back to in ברכות Berachot there's a.
whole fantastic section there of discussion of the laws of עיקר וטפל
ikar ve-tafel by ברכות, brachos,
and there's a discussion: what about if you eat certain very, very
sweet fruits and then after you eat them you have to eat
bread? But the bread is totally טפל tafel to the act of
eating the fruit. The fruit is so sweet it overwhelms you and
that you have to then afterwards eat something else to take the
sweetness out of your mouth. And it talks about it's the fruit
from גינוסר. Ginosar. גינוסר Ginosar is on the near the coast of
the כנרת. Kineret. They have a kibbutz there now where they grow
a lot of bananas.
So the גמרא Gemara in ברכות brachos is describing the experience of
the fruits of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael are so incredibly sweet, are
so incredibly overwhelming.
So it's actually interesting here, the problem: sweet fruits go bad quickly.
Maybe if they're not so sweet, they can last for a longer
time, which is an interesting suggestion. Okay. So that's the discussion of
חרס, cheres, but משוח לסוף כחרס. mashuach le-sof ke-cheres. כלב? Caleb? What
about כלב? Caleb? דכתיב ויתנו לכלב את חברון כאשר דבר משה ויורש
משם את שלשה בני הענק.
dichsiv vayisnu le-Calev es Hevron ka'asher diber Moshe vayoresh misham
es shlosha bnei ha-anak.
So they gave to כלב Caleb the city of חברון. Hevron. Well
we know רש"י Rashi already in the פסוקים psukim tells us at
one point why why does it seem like כלב Caleb wasn't with
the other מרגלים? meraglim? It was the מדרש Midrashic tradition is that
כלב Caleb went to go pray at מערת המכפלה, Me'aras ha-Machpelah, which
becomes the source of actually going to מערת המכפלה Me'aras ha-Machpelah to
pray, that has some kind of a special significance and going to
קבר אבות kever avos in general.
And so כלב Caleb was given the city of חברון Hevron as
משה Moshe assigned him, and when he went to go conquer it,
כלב Caleb went on his own, meaning most of the time the
people would go, the whole national army to go conquer at different
regions of ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. For the city of חברון, Hevron,
כלב Caleb went himself and he conquered it and he killed the
three giants who were still there. Right, it was called קרית ארבע
Kiryat Arba because there were four giants and then one of them
was killed and then others, so he killed all three. Okay. חברון
עיר מקלט הוי? Hevron ir miklat havei? Wasn't חברון Hevron an עיר
מקלט? ir miklat? And we know the ערי מקלט arei miklat went
to the לויים. Leviim. The six ערי מקלט arei miklat were six
out of the either forty-two or forty-eight cities for the לויים. Leviim.
Okay. דאמר אביי, d'amar Abaye, פרבר הא. parvar ha. So he's talking
about the suburbs. דכתיב ואת שדי העיר ואת חצריה נתנו לכלב בן
יפנה באחוזתו. dichsiv ve-es sdei ha-ir ve-es chatzereha nasnu le-Calev ben Yefuneh
be-achuzaso.
So the city of חברון Hevron itself within the wall must have
been for the לויים. Leviim. But outside of the city of חברון
Hevron and outside obviously the מגרש, migrash, the field area assigned to
the לויים, Leviim, but there and there's a debate in the ראשונים
Rishonim about how big it is, but basically you have your city,
this is a dry mark, you have a city, you have some
מגרש migrash around the outside, and then the rest, we can imagine
some whole area that's suburban חברון Hevron and that's that all goes
to כלב. Caleb. This goes to the לויים, Leviim, and this goes
to the לויים. Leviim. So this is the city, this is the
special,
precise boundaries of the מגרש migrash for the לויים, Leviim, and then
כלב Caleb gets the the environs of the city of חברון. Hevron.
But what it means fundamentally and now חברון Hevron also within the
territory of יהודה, Yehuda, so כלב Caleb is able to live in
the tribe that he would have been assigned just like יהושע. Joshua.
יהושע Joshua is living in the city of, now I forget the
word, תמנת סרח. Timnas Serach. So תמנת סרח Timnas Serach is in
אפרים, Ephraim, so יהושע Joshua can live there and his ancestors, his
descendants will live in his tribe, and כלב Caleb will live in
the city of חברון Hevron which is in יהודה. Yehuda. So perfect
match. Okay. We continue with the גמרא Gemara starting from the next
משנה, Mishna, and we'll see how far we get. Tomorrow's דף daf
is very long, so Rabbi Lindzer did want me to try to
get a little bit onto tomorrow's דף. daf. We'll see how far
we get. Okay. So the משנה Mishna says אחד הבן ואחד הבת
בנחלה. echad ha-ben ve-echad ha-bas be-nachala.
Sounds like a son and a daughter are totally equivalent in inheritance,
which we already know is not true and which is going to
be the גמרא's Gemara first main contention. But what it means is
that when a single son and a single daughter are inheriting, they
basically follow the same rules in terms of how they pass it
on to their descendants and obviously, but the son comes before the
daughter, so in that way they're not equal. אלא שהבן נוטל פי
שנים בנכסי האב. ela she-ha-ben notel pi shnayim be-nichsei ha-av. One of
the only few differences is that a son, a firstborn son can
take a double portion. ואינו נוטל פי שנים בנכסי האם. ve-eino notel
pi shnayim be-nichsei ha-em. But there's no double portion inheriting from the
mother. והבנות ניזונות מנכסי האב ואינן ניזונות מנכסי האם. ve-ha-banos nizonos mi-nichsei
ha-av ve-einan nizonos mi-nichsei ha-em.
And daughters who are on an annuity support מזונות mezonos payments from
their estate can collect that from their father's estate but not from
their mother's estate. So those are some of the differences between a
son and a daughter. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says מאי אחד
הבן ואחד הבת לנחלה? mai echad ha-ben ve-echad ha-bas le-nachala?
How can the משנה Mishna say that a son and a daughter
are equivalent for נחלה? nachala? אילימא... ilima... דירתי כהדדי, de'yarti ke'hadadei, התנן
בן קודם לבת. ha'tenan ben kodem le'bat.
So aren't we saying it's contradicting what we saw previously in the
previous earlier משנה Mishnah that a son inherits before before daughter? כל
יוצאי ירך של בן קודמין לבת. kol yotzei yerech shel ben kodmin
labat.
And any descendant of the son will inherit before the daughter inherits.
So סימן נפשם, siman nafsham, this is going to help the next
sections of the סוגיא. sugya. אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק הכי קאמר:
Amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak hachi ka'amar: this is what we're talking
about. Okay, אחד הבן ואחד הבת נוטלין בראוי כבמוחזק. echad haben ve'echad
habat notlin biraui kivemuchzak.
So the son and the daughter basically inherit properties equivalently between ראוי
raui and מוחזק. muchzak.
ראוי raui being the property... now I got mixed up. The רשב"ם
Rashbam explains: אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק הכי קאמר אחד הבן ואחד
הבת במקום שאין בן שוין בנחלה ליטול מה שהיה ראוי לאביהם.
Amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak hachi ka'amar echad haben ve'echad habat bimkom
she'ein ben shavin banachalah litol mah shehayah
raui la'avihem.
That is when the father is inheriting from something else and then
it, meaning the father inherits something not from his father but from
some other relative, then these descendants, either son or daughter, will inherit
through their father equivalently. That is the ראוי, raui, that is whatever
would be suitable to go to the father under any kind of
a circumstance, or more generally inheritance circumstances, and במוחזק, bamuchzak, מוחזק muchzak
being the properties that the father has now. So the son and
the daughter will have equal rights in,
if the father has this one son or this one daughter, the
properties will transfer to that child equivalently, whether it's ראוי, raui, whether
it's something that's going to transfer from some more distant relative, or
ראוי, raui, right, and מוחזק, muchzak, מוחזק muchzak property that you're actually
already in control of and you already have holdings of. Okay. דהוה
אמינא dahavamina being
that
you might think a daughter would
would only have a נחלה nachalah rights, but not necessarily to other
properties, right. Right, maybe the rule of a daughter inheriting is a
special exemption, special rule that applies to an ancestral piece of land,
but doesn't apply more broadly to the father's estate. So the משנה
Mishnah comes to say אחד הבן ואחד הבת. echad haben ve'echad habat.
They're equivalent.
Okay, so הא נמי תנינא, ha nami tanina, we have another ברייתא
baraita about this: בנות צלפחד נטלו שלשה חלקים בנחלה. benot Tzelofchad natlu
shloshah chalakim banachalah. The daughters of צלפחד, Tzelofchad, five daughters, right,
took control actually of three portions of land in the inheritance: חלק
אביהן שהיה מיוצאי מצרים, chelek avihen shehayah miyotzei Mitzrayim, they took their
father's property because he left Egypt, וחלקו עם אחיו בנכסי חפר, vechelko
im echav benichsei Chefer, and his portion among his brothers of what
they inherited from their father חפר. Chefer. ועוד מאי? ve'od mai? So
what does it, meaning so then why do we need to continue
with this, the rest point of the משנה? Mishnah? אלא, ela,
so מאי אלא, mai ela, what is the אלא? ela? Meaning why
does
the משנה Mishnah say אלא, ela, right? The משנה Mishnah says אחד
הבן ואחד הבת בנחלה אלא שהבן נוטל. echad haben ve'echad habat banachalah
ela shehaben notel. So why does it have to say אלא? ela?
Meaning why the אלא, ela, rather, is coming to make some kind
of an exclusion. אלא אמר רב פפא הכי קאמר: Ela amar Rav
Papa hachi ka'amar: this is what it's saying: אחד הבן ואחד הבת
נוטלין חלק בבכורה, echad haben ve'echad habat notlin chelek bibechorah, a son
and a daughter can take a portion of the firstborn's portion. So
הא נמי תנינא, ha nami tanina, we had another ברייתא baraita that
already says that: שהיה בכור נוטל שני חלקים, shehayah bechor notel shnei
chalakim, that the, that in a case where the son is a
בכור bechor he takes a double portion. So then the purpose... so
the daughter, his daughter will be able to inherit the בכור's bechor
portion from her father, so it also makes sense. So why should,
why do we need that in this משנה Mishnah either? ועוד מאי
אלא? ve'od mai ela? And we still didn't understand why the משנה
Mishnah says אלא. ela. אלא אמר רב אשי. Ela amar Rav Ashi.
I mean it's confusing every time we have אלא, ela, we have
אלא מאי אלא ela mai ela and then אלא אמר ela amar
right so. אלא אמר רב אשי הכי קאמר: Ela amar Rav Ashi
hachi ka'amar: this is what we're saying רב אשי Rav Ashi says:
אחד בן בין הבנים ואחד בת בין הבנות. echad ben bein habanim
ve'echad bat bein habanot.
So a son among other sons gets a single portion, a daughter
among other daughters gets a single portion, and they're equivalent. אם אמר
ייירש כל נכסי דבריו קיימין. im amar yerash kol nechasai devarav kayamin.
If he says that this, this should inherit all my properties, like
he tries to write like a kind of a living will almost
here, right? So he says they should inherit my properties, דבריו קיימין,
devarav kayamin, his words are upheld. כמאן? keman? כרבי יוחנן בן ברוקה.
ki'Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka. That's like רבי יוחנן בן ברוקה's Rabbi Yochanan
ben Beroka position. הא קתני לה לקמן רבי יוחנן בן ברוקה אומר
אם אמר על מי שראוי ליורשו: ha katanila lekaman Rabbi Yochanan ben
Beroka omer im amar al mi sheraui leyorsho: if he said that
about someone who would be fitting to inherit from him already, this
person should inherit all my property, דבריו קיימין, devarav kayamin, then the
words are upheld. על מי שאינו ראוי ליורשו אין דבריו קיימין. al
mi she'eino raui leyorsho ein devarav kayamin. But if you say it
about someone who's not fitting to inherit from you, then we don't
uphold your words because we take them as meaningless. That is if
a person designates all of their property to be inherited to that
child. Even a daughter. That is even in a case if it's
בת בין הבנות bat bein ha-banot or בן בין הבנים, ben bein
ha-banim, then that would work. But if it was let's say בת
בין הבנים, bat bein ha-banim, right, it wouldn't work.
It sounds like it wouldn't work because she wouldn't be able to
inherit in a case where there are sons. וכי תימא v'khi teima
קא סתם לן ka stam lan כרבי יוחנן בן ברוקא? k'Rabbi Yochanan
ben Beroka?
You're really going to tell me that a סתם משנה stam mishna
is according to the position of רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא, Rabbi Yochanan
ben Beroka, which is a minority position, rejected position? So סתם ואחר
כך מחלוקת היא, stam v'akhar kakh makhloket hi,
because that's a משנה mishna later, and the general rule is if
we have a סתם משנה stam mishna first followed by the מחלוקת,
makhloket, then that's so then we say that the מחלוקת makhloket bears
on the סתם. stam. Usually if we say מחלוקת ואחר כך סתם,
makhloket v'akhar kakh stam, it means that the סתם stam was paskening
which was the correct position from the מחלוקת makhloket because the מחלוקת
makhloket came first. This is like we had a few a few
weeks ago, תפוס לשון אחרון tfos lashon akharon kind of thing, right?
That if you have מחלוקת ואחר כך סתם, makhloket v'akhar kakh stam,
the סתם stam comes to clarify which position in the מחלוקת makhloket
we've adopted. But we had סתם ואחר כך מחלוקת, stam v'akhar kakh
makhloket, then great, we have a סתם משנה stam mishna here. The
משנה mishna later reveals to us that it's actually a מחלוקת makhloket
and the position in our משנה mishna is רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא,
Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka, which is the rejected position. Okay. וסתם ואחר
כך מחלוקת אין הלכה כסתם, v'stam v'akhar kakh makhloket ein halakha k'stam,
and the general rule is you don't follow the סתם. stam. You
have to follow the rules of כללי הפסק klalei ha-psak for for
who's the מחלוקת. makhloket. Generally we would say הלכה כסתם משנה, halakha
k'stam mishna,
but if it's followed by מחלוקת makhloket that bears on the same
topic, then you have to judge it by the מחלוקת. makhloket. Okay.
ועוד מאי אלא? v'od mai ella?
We still didn't address what the word אלא ella comes to teach.
This is the pattern of this סוגיא. sugya. That is, the סוגיא
sugya is all attempts to explain the first line of the משנה
mishna that then get blocked. By the time they reach the word
אלא, ella, the explanation doesn't seem to fit.
Okay. ועוד מאי אלא? v'od mai ella? אלא אמר מר בר רב
אשי. ella amar Mar bar Rav Ashi. So מר בר רב אשי,
Mar bar Rav Ashi, very late אמורא, amora, says הכי קאמר: hakhi
ka'amar: אחד הבן ואחד הבת שוין בנכסי האם ובנכסי האב. ekhad ha-ben
v'ekhad ha-bat shavin b'nikhsei ha-em u-v'nikhsei ha-av. So sons and daughters are
equivalent regarding the inheritance from their mother or from their father, אלא,
ella,
and the משנה mishna says, right, אלא שהבן נוטל פי שנים בנכסי
האב. ella she-ha-ben notel pi shnayim b'nikhsei ha-av. But a son has
a special rule that the son is able to collect a double
portion as a בכור, bekhor, ואינו נוטל פי שנים בנכסי האם. v'eino
notel pi shnayim b'nikhsei ha-em. But he doesn't he doesn't collect double
portion from his mother's property. So that's the end of the סוגיא.
sugya. That is the structure, the way the structure worked, and we
saw who it was. It was רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, that's the
נון. nun. The פא pei was רב פפא. Rav Pappa. The שין
shin was רב אשי, Rav Ashi, אשי. Ashi.
And then the מם mem is מר בר רב אשי. Mar bar
Rav Ashi. So נפשם Nafsham tells us the structure of the סוגיא.
sugya. It's interesting that it's a four-part סוגיא sugya actually, which is
not so common, but the point is that each of them had
an attempt to explain the first line of the משנה. mishna. How
does the first line of the משנה mishna make sense? But the
אלא ella clause has to fit with the explanation of the first
part. So the distinction between a בן ben and a בת bat
or the, sorry, the equivalence between a בן ben and a בת
bat has to be made in such a context that the exception
to the rule would be אלא שהבן נוטל פי שנים בנכסי האב,
ella she-ha-ben notel pi shnayim b'nikhsei ha-av, which according to מר בר
רב אשי's Mar bar Rav Ashi explanation fits. That is, מר בר
רב אשי Mar bar Rav Ashi says a son and a daughter
are equivalent in general regarding inheritance from either their father or their
mother, but the difference is the special rule of a בכור bekhor
getting a second portion applies only to inheriting from the father but
not to the mother. That's מר בר רב אשי's Mar bar Rav
Ashi explanation. תנו רבנן. tanu rabanan. The next ברייתא braita continues לתת
לו פי שנים. latet lo pi shnayim. So this is from the
beginning of כי תצא. Ki Teitzei. כי תצא Ki Teitzei discusses first
the problem or the מצוה mitzvah in a case of אשת יפת
תואר, eshet yifat to'ar, a man finds a captive prisoner in war
and wishes to marry her, and then the גמרא, gemara, the פסוקים
psukim go on to describe a man who has two wives and
he prefers the wife who has the younger child. His firstborn son
is from the wife who he does not love as much. That
happened to יעקב, Yaakov, happened to אלקנה, Elkana, happened to a number
of people. And the general rule happened to אברהם ושרה Avraham v'Sarah
also, right, in some way or another. And so in that case,
the תורה Torah forbids לא יוכל לבכר lo yukhal l'vaker את בן
האהובה, et ben ha-ahuva, no I know but
I'm forgetting the verb, sorry, I'm lost in my head a little
bit. Okay anyway, so you have to, so the פסוק pasuk says
לתת לו פי שנים, latet lo pi shnayim, that the בכור, bekhor,
the בכור, bekhor, the בן השנואה, ben ha-snu'ah, את בן השנואה יכיר
לתת לו פי שנים. et ben ha-snu'ah yakir latet lo pi shnayim.
You have to recognize which one
is... Even if it's בן השנואה *ben hasnuah*, the son of the
less desirable of the two wives, in order to give him a
preferable the double portion. So the גמרא *Gemara* says פי שנים כאחד
*pi shnayim ke'echad* אתה אומר *ata omer* פי שנים כאחד *pi shnayim
ke'echad* או אינו אלא *o eino ela* פי שנים בכל הנכסים *pi
shnayim bechol hanechasim*. So what does it mean פי שנים *pi shnayim*?
Does פי שנים *pi shnayim* mean פי שנים כאחד *pi shnayim ke'echad*,
means like רשב"ם Rashbam *Rashbam* says פי שנים כאחד *pi shnayim ke'echad*
כנגד אחד מן האחים נוטל *keneged echad min ha'achim notel* פי שנים
*pi shnayim* שאם היו חמישה אחים *she'im hayu chamisha achim* חולקין הנכסים
בשישה חלקים *cholkin hanechasim beshisha chalakim* ונוטל הבכור פי שנים מהם *venotel
habechor pi shnayim mehem*? He gets two times whatever would be a
normal subdivision. So if there are five sons, you take the entire
inheritance and split it into six portions and he gets two-sixths and
everyone else gets one-sixth. That's what it would mean פי שנים כאחד
*pi shnayim ke'echad*.
Or do you mean פי שנים *pi shnayim* אינו אלא *eino ela*
פי שנים בכל הנכסים *pi shnayim bechol hanechasim*? Do you mean פי
שנים *pi shnayim* of כל הנכסים *kol hanechasim* which רשב"ם *Rashbam* explains
בכל הנכסים *bechol hanechasim* שנוטל פי שנים בכולם *shenotel pi shnayim bekulam*?
You get double part of everything. That is what...
So the distinction here is do you get a double portion of
the meaning you get two times a regular portion or do you
get
two
times the total of the rest of it if that makes
sense. What? Meaning meaning meaning the three of us are going to
inherit. I get double what you get and double what Gloria gets
or like
this is a whole נחלה nachala *nachala*. There are three sons, let's
make it easier, right? There are three sons. So do we say
you divide it into
four
parts and he gets, right, so this is one, one, well three
is not going to work, we need five. One sec. Okay. We
need a bigger number. There are five sons. Okay. Do we divide
it into six portions and he gets two and then everyone else
gets one?
Or do we divide it again for five sons?
You leave this?
Oh sure, sorry. Let's move this. We said six, right?
Okay, so I'm going to do color coding.
Okay, purple is for the בכור bechor *bechor*. Okay. So this is
number one, this is בכור bechor *bechor* פי שנים *pi shnayim* כאחד
*ke'echad*. This is כאחד *ke'echad*.
Okay and we have the same one and now we're trying to
say if you take in this case you split the whole thing
such that the portion that will go to the other four... It's
split into eight.
Yeah,
into eight, right.
It's split into half and then the half into four.
Right, half goes to four and half half goes to the בכור
bechor *bechor*. So he'll get a pretty significant portion.
Right.
No, it needs to be double whatever everyone else gets. Oh, so
it will need to be even more. It will need to be
in like he gets two-thirds of the entire inheritance.
So here he gets only one-third, right? His total is for five
sons he gets one-third and here he gets two-thirds.
And then everyone...
it needs to be double whatever everyone else gets, right, so they
get very small נחלה nachala *nachala*.
This is with five sons. With certain number of sons it will
be more more equitable, but because there are a lot of sons
it's going to be very minimal here, right? He gets a two-thirds,
right? It's because it's על פי שנים *al pi shnayim* שנים בכל
הנכסים *shnayim bechol hanechasim*. He gets two parts out of three of
the whole
property. Okay, so ודינו *vedino*, so it's logical. We can learn it
from קל וחומר *kal vachomer*. Okay. חלקו עם אחד וחלקו עם חמישה
*chelko im echad vechelko im chamisha*. It's whether you divide it with
one one son or five sons. מה חלקו עם אחד פי שנים
כאחד *ma chelko im echad pi shnayim ke'echad*. If there meaning there's
only one son.
So when he gets a double portion it means a double portion
of what he normally meaning of what however many sons would have
gotten it would just be it's just like this, right? You would
say כאחד *ke'echad*. Meaning if there were only two, so he would
they would divide it two-thirds, one-third. Okay. אף חלקו עם חמישה פי
שנים כאחד *af chelko im chamisha pi shnayim ke'echad*. או *o* כלך
לדרך זו *keilech laderach zo* חלקו עם אחד וחלקו עם חמישה *chelko
im echad vechelko im chamisha*. Or are you going to say it
like this: if you divide it between whether there is one son
or whether there are five sons. מה חלקו עם אחד פי שנים
בכל הנכסים *ma chelko im echad pi shnayim bechol hanechasim*. Then you'll
say the opposite way. You'll say, oh, he should get double of
the two parts, two-thirds of the entire thing. אף חלקו עם חמישה
פי שנים בכל הנכסים *af chelko im chamisha pi shnayim bechol hanechasim*.
So then you should say for five also he should get two-thirds
of the entire inheritance, right? Because in a case where there are
only two, only two brothers, right, they both agree that in a
case... both systems of subdivision agree that with two brothers, right, the
בכור bechor will get two-thirds, no matter what, because either it's two-thirds
of the whole thing, or it's two times what a single one
gets. So which way becomes the model? Is you say you always
the בכור always gets two-thirds of the whole property? Or do you
say that the בכור just gets double a single share? That's the
question. So you can't learn it because he says,
כלך לדרך זו חלקי אחד וחלקי חמישה מה חלקי אחד kelech lederech
zo chelko echad vechelko chamisha mah chelko echad פי שניים בכל הנכסים
pi shnayim bechol hanechasim should get two-thirds אף חלקי חמישה af chelko
chamisha פי שניים בכל הנכסים. pi shnayim bechol hanechasim. תלמוד לומר talmud
lomar והיה ביום הנחילו את בניו. vehaya beyom hanchilo et banav. So
the פסוק pasuk comes to say on the day that he divides
his property among his sons, התורה ריבתה נחלה אצל אחים. haTorah rivtah
nachala etzel achim. The Torah increases the amount of נחלה nachala. that
the different brothers will be able to get. הנחילו את בניו. hanchilo
et banav. That is,
הא אין עליך לדון כלשון האחרון אלא כלשון הראשון. ha ein alecha
ladun kelashon ha'acharon ela kelashon harishon. You should follow the first interpretation
and not the second interpretation. That is, it should go double a
single single share. Because each son is going to get a single
share. That's והיה ביום הנחילו את בניו. vehaya beyom hanchilo et banav.
Each נחלה nachala. that goes to the בנים banim is an equivalent
share. So it can't be, it would be totally inequitable to say
that it's two-thirds goes to this brother and one-third, you know, in
this case right, there are five brothers, so he should get one-third
because it's just double a single share? But here he should get
two-thirds of the whole thing and each of them only gets one-twelfth?
That would be... Right, it's not particularly...
Meaning, you could say in the first one where there's two of
them, he gets two-thirds. he gets double what the rest of the
property is. Right.
The question is, does this model mean two times or does it
mean two-thirds? Right. That's the question for what the בכור gets.
And the example of two brothers doesn't help.
No, exactly. The point is that two brothers' case everyone, both models
agree. So which version do you extrapolate from?
But isn't that their point that you're extrapolating from, you're extrapolating that
it's double the one person?
No, because they learn it from the פסוק pasuk והיה ביום הנחילו
את בניו. vehaya beyom hanchilo et banav. So התורה ריבתה נחלה אצל
אחים haTorah rivtah nachala etzel achim that each of the brothers still,
whatever the brothers get, counts as a נחלה. So this version, they're
getting such a small portion, it's sort of not really fair that
each of the brothers is going to have a real נחלה. So
this one is more equitable or more, more reasonable conclusion to draw,
that he should just get double. Which what the רשב"ם says from
the first line, ריבתה נחלה שלא יטול פי שניים בכל הנכסים היכא
דאיכא שניים ושלושה אחים מלבדו.
rivtah nachala shelo yitol pi shnayim bechol hanechasim heicha
de'ika shnayim ushlosha achim milvado. When there start to be so many
other brothers inheriting, then this becomes a totally untenable position. That is,
if you look at this case you can ask which model is
it? Does the בכור get two-thirds of the whole property or does
he get two times a single share? Once you start having more
heirs competing for the same property, the two-thirds model makes no sense.
It's not really a logical argument as much as just to say
that position is not, is not reasonable. Okay.
Okay, so let's stop there because the next part goes into a
sort of a different topic. I hope everyone has a wonderful day
and just plugging tonight there's a special all-Riverdale wide program at the
Young Israel North Riverdale for יום ירושלים Yom Yerushalayim in collaboration with
a lot of different שולס shuls so everyone should enjoy that and
be there.